Guide to the Paul Moody Atkins Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Paul Moody Atkins papers
1749-1976
MS 41
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
17
(47 boxes, 2 folios)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, printed material, writings, clippings, diaries, photographs, and miscellanea relating to Paul Moody Atkins, a financial management consultant, international economic and banking expert, author, educator, and special liquidator of securities for the U.S. Comptroller of the Currency (1932-1937). Atkins' professional work in Peru (1931), French West Africa (1940-1941), Iran (1943-1945), Greece (1947-1948), and Japan (1948) are documented through correspondence, memoranda, reports, and other material. His role on financial commissions and as a private consultant are further detailed in correspondence with Mrs. Atkins and family members. Financial data from Atkins' service as special liquidator details the security transactions and operations of this office from 1932-1937. Other professional materials document Atkins' participation on the American Commission to Negotiate Peace (1919), the National Management Council (1950-1951), as an educator and lecturer at Rutgers University (1956-1962), and as a private lecturer (1960-1977). Family papers include the World War I diary of Henri Bergier, Atkins' father-in-law, who was a judge in occupied Cabrai, France during the First World War.
Atkins, Paul M. (Paul Moody), 1892-
General
Henri Bergier's World War I diary, both the original and the typescript, is in French.
Conditions Governing Access
Henri Bergier's World War I diary is available on microfilm. The original is not to be used without permission of the reference librarian.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Paul Moody Atkins in several accessions from 1944-1976.
Existence and Location of Copies
The diary, correspondence, and photographs of Henri Bergier are available on microfilm (1,427 frames on 2 reels, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM168.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Professional Files, 1919-1976. II. Family and Personal Papers, 1749-1976.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, printed material, writings, clippings, diaries, photographs, and miscellanea relating to Paul Moody Atkins, a financial management consultant, international economic and banking expert, author, educator, and special liquidator of securities for the U. S. Comptroller of the Currency (1932-1937).
Atkins' professional work in Peru (1931), French West Africa (1940-1941), Iran (1943-1945), Greece (1947-1948), and Japan (1948) are documented through correspondence, memoranda, reports, and other materials. His role in financial commissions and as a private consultant are further detailed in correspondence with Mrs. Atkins and family members. Financial data from Atkins' service as special liquidator details the security transactions and operations of this office from 1932-1937. Other professional materials document Atkins' participation on the American Commission to Negotiate Peace (1919), the National Management Council (1950-1951), as an educator and lecturer at Rutgers University (1956-1962), and as a private lecturer (1960-1977).
Family papers include the World War I diary of Henri Bergier, Atkins' father-in-law, who was a judge in occupied Cabrai, France during the First World War.
The Atkins Papers (17 linear ft.) are arranged in two series.
SERIES I, PROFESSIONAL FILES, 1919-1976, contains correspondence, memoranda, reports, printed material, photographs, clippings, and miscellanea detailing Atkins' work for private industry, on government commissions, and in academic posts as a private consultant, banking adviser, educator, and author. Many aspects of his work in the United States, Peru, French West Africa, Iran, Greece, and Japan relating to national and international finance, business, and politics are documented.
Atkins' work within the United States included his appointment as special liquidator of securities for the U. S. Comptroller (1932-1937). Financial data and files document the security transactions and office operations which Atkins supervised. By his own account, Atkins oversaw the disposition of more than one-quarter of a billion dollars in frozen securities from insolvent national banks. Clippings, correspondence, office files, and articles also detail the actions and operations of the special liquidator's office (boxes 7-11).
Atkins' foreign assignments and positions were several. He travelled to Peru in 1931 as public credits expert on the Kemmerer Financial Mission. Published reports in both Spanish and English, printed material, and miscellanea detail that body's efforts to stabilize the Peruvian banking system (boxes 5-6). He later served as foreign representative for Balfour, Guthrie, and Company, Ltd., in French West Africa (1941). Correspondence, clippings, maps, postcards, photographs, and miscellanea document Atkins' property negotiations with the French government and his covert observations of German military activity for the United States government. Atkins' travels through Portugal, Maderia, the Cape Verde Islands, and Portuguese Guinea are also detailed (boxes 15-16).
Atkins' work in Iran as economic adviser to the Ministry of Iran and as a member of the Millspaugh Mission (1943-1945) is documented in correspondence, memoranda, reports, clippings, scrapbooks, and miscellanea (boxes 17-18). Attempts to direct the tobacco and opium monopolies and and a later project to reorganize government-owned factories are documented, as is the long-running disagreement between Atkins and Arthur C. Millspaugh, head of the U. S. commission sent to help control the rising inflation rate in the Iranian economy. Atkins outlined his economic and political observations in letters and reports to U. S. government officials, and in personal correspondence to his wife which the State Department requested remain strictly confidential. Additional material includes a copy of a 1941 journal written by William McE. Miller, an American Presbyterian missionary in Iran.
Atkins served as acting director of the Public Finance Division, the Commerce and Supply division, and the Industry Division of the American Mission for Aid to Greece (1947-1948). Reports, correspondence, clippings, and printed material document attempts to rehabilitate and financially redevelop Greece in the aftermath of World War II (boxes 19-20). As a banking adviser to General Douglas MacArthur's staff in Japan (1948), Atkins also contributed to revitalization efforts there. He accumulated financial data, reports, clippings, correspondence, and miscellanea on Japanese banks, including the Bank of Kobe, the Sumitomo Bank, and the Tokai Bank (box 21).
Student manuals, course materials, and a series of radio lectures detail Atkins' academic career at Rutgers University (1956-1977). Although a teaching specialist in business administration, Atkins lectured his radio audiences on a multitude of national and international topics, including the Vietnamese conflict, the Middle East and the Watergate scandal.
Atkins held several other positions during his long and diverse career. He served as secretary for the subcommittee on Czechoslovakian Affairs for the American Commission to Negotiate Peace (1919), and as a delegate to the International Management Conference (1924). Atkins also held the positions of treasurer with the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation (1937-1938), vice president and director of Grant and Atkins, Incorporated (1939-1940), and project manager for the National Management Council (1950-1951). Correspondence, reports, printed material, and miscellanea document these aspects of Atkins' career.
Writings(boxes 26-33) contains published and unpublished articles, books, and essays relating to all facets of Atkins' career. Published articles include a series of works on industrial management and is complimented by one of Atkins' books,Textbook of Industrial Cost Accounting(1924). Unpublished works include several essays on Atkins' foreign experiences, in addition to the more common financial and business writings. An unpublished manuscript, "A History of the United States for People of Other Countries," which Atkins wrote with his wife (and translated into French and Spanish versions) is also arranged in this series.
SERIES II, FAMILY AND PERSONAL PAPERS, 1749-1976, contains correspondence, diaries, photographs, printed material, memorabilia, and miscellanea relating to members of the Atkins family, including Paul Moody Atkins and Henri Bergier.
Family Papers contains a diary compiled by Henri Bergier, father-in-law to Paul Moody Atkins. Bergier was a judge in Cabrai, France during the German occupation of 1914-1918. His diary, written as letters to family members, is a daily account of life in Cabrai from August 26, 1914 to October 10, 1918. The diary and a typescript prepared by Atkins and his wife are in French (boxes 34-35). Both items are available on microfilm, (HM 168).
Genealogical material on the Atkins family, including an 1847 biography of the Moody family and a 1749 sermon delivered at the ordination of Abraham Williams (1727-1784) are arranged in this series. Family memorabilia such as birth and marriage certificates and photographs of several family members are also organized here (boxes 36-38).
Personal papers contains correspondence, student papers, and travel logs of Paul Moody Atkins unrelated to his professional career. These materials include letters and copies of material Atkins received from the F. B. I. and the C. I. A. following his requests for agency files on his activities (box 34), a copy of his Ph. D. dissertation from the Université de Paris (box 42), and miscellanea.
Biographical / Historical
Paul Moody Atkins was born in Boston, Massachusetts on April 3, 1892. He died on January 31, 1977 in New Jersey. Atkins was a cost accountant, management engineer, educator, special liquidator of securities for the U. S. Comptroller's Office (1932-1937), financial and management consultant, international economic and banking expert, lecturer, radio commentator, and author.
Atkins participated in the Kemmerer Financial Mission to Peru (1931), as the foreign representative of the Balfour, Guthrie, and Company, Ltd. in French West Africa (1940-1941), as an economic adviser to the "Millspaugh Mission" in Iran (1943-1945), as a banking specialist on the American Mission for Aid to Greece (1947-1948), and as a banking adviser to the army in Japan (1948). He also held the position of special liquidator of securities for the U.S. Comptroller of the Currency (1932-1937). Atkins taught business administration at Rutgers University and delivered speeches and radio commentaries on international affairs.
He received his B. A. from Yale in 1914, and his M. A. in 1915. Atkins doctorate was awarded by the Université de Paris in 1925. He married Genevieve Bergier in 1920; they had three children.
Accounting; Banks and banking; Business and politics; Business; Industrial management; International finance; World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives, French; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1939-1945; Africa, French-speaking West; Africa; Greece -- Economic conditions; Iran -- Economic conditions; Japan -- Economic conditions; Latin America; Middle East; Peru -- Economic conditions; United States -- Economic conditions; United States -- Foreign economic conditions; United States -- Foreign relations; United States -- Politics and government; Diaries; Atkins, Paul M. (Paul Moody), 1892-; Bergier, Henri; Miller, William McEwen; Millspaugh, Arthur Chester, 1883-1955; Williams, Abraham; Atkins family; United States. Treasury. U.S. Comptroller of the Currency; Yale University -- Students; Alfred P. Sloan Foundation; United States. American Commission to Negotiate Peace; American Missions for Aid to Greece; Balfour, Guthrie, and Company, Ltd; Kemmerer Financial Mission to Peru
- PROFESSIONAL FILES, 1919-1936; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in sections which correspond to the sequence of professional positions which Atkins held during his career.
  Atkins professional writings are arranged in a single section, at the end of the series.
  Each section contains material arranged alphabetically by type, and chronologically within the type of material.
  - American Commission to Negotiate Peace
    - General
      - Articles, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Clippings, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Memorabilia, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Poetry, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Printed material, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - American Committee to Protect Against Tuberculosis in France: printed material, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Committee on Czecho-Slovak affairs
      - Correspondence, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Minutes, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Statistics, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - International Management Conference
    - Memorabilia, 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Photographs, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Printed material, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ames, Emerich, and Co.
    - Correspondence, 1929-1931 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Reports
      - Cost Control for the Pickard Studies, Inc., 1926 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - "Economic Trends in Hungary", 1926 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - "An Analysis of the Investment Position of an Illinois Life Insurance Company", [ca. 1926-1931] (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - "Secondary Reserves of Banks" (draft), 1928 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - "Organization of a Holding Company for Banks", 1928 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - "Individual Investment Reserves", 1928 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - "Bank Secondary Reserves and Investments", 1928 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - "The Investment of Corporation Reserves", 1928 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - "Secondary Reserves of Banks", 1928 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
      - "Course of Training for Ames, Emerich and Co. Salesmen", 1929 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - "Bank, Corporation...Chicago Office", undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - Miscellanea, 1928-1930, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Kemmerer Financial Mission to Peru
    - Clippings, 1931, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence: family, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Memorabilia, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Printed material, 1926, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Printed material, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 31-32)
    - Public Credit Report (in English and Spanish), 1931 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Report on the Public Credit of Peru (in Spanish), 1931 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Tables of Amortization and Interest, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Special Liquidator of Securities
    - Analysis of Sales
      - 1936-1937 (Box 7, Folder 36-37)
      - Section I, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 38)
      - Section II (1), 1936 (Box 7, Folder 39)
      - Section II (2), 1936 (Box 7, Folder 40)
      - Section II (3), 1936 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Analysis of Sales by Brokers
      - Reconstruction Finance Corporation Account
        - 1934-1936 (Box 7, Folder 42-45)
        - Recapitulation, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 46)
      - Regular account
        - 1932 (Box 7, Folder 47-50)
        - 1933-1936 (Box 8, Folder 51-66)
        - Related materials
          - Expenses, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 67)
          - Information re: account reconciliation, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 68)
          - Monthly control: account reconciliation, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 69-70)
          - Names of brokers, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 71)
          - Recapitulation, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 72-73)
      - Special cases
        - 1932-1936 (Box 9, Folder 74-76)
        - Related materials: recapitulation, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - Books: Security Dealers of North America, 1932 (Box 9, Folder 78)
    - Clippings, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 79)
    - Correspondence, 1932-1939 (Box 10, Folder 80)
    - Documentary material, 1936-1937, undated (Box 10, Folder 81)
    - First Pentad, [ca1932, 1938, 1963] (Box 10, Folder 82)
    - Forms, undated (Box 10, Folder 83)
    - Payroll, 1932-1937 (Box 10, Folder 84-88)
    - Reports
      - "A Report on the Secondary Reserves and Investments of the First National Bank of...NY", 1931 (Box 10, Folder 89)
      - "A Report on the Secondary Reserves and Investments of the First National Bank", 1931 (Box 10, Folder 90)
      - "The Secondary Reserve and Investment Accounts of the First National Bank", 1931(?) (Box 10, Folder 91)
      - "Claflin, Warren and Co., Inc. General Policy Report", 1932 (Box 10, Folder 92)
      - " Report on the State of Alabama", 1932 April (Box 48)
      - "Analysis of the Credit Position of Miami, Florida, Bonds", 1935 (Box 10, Folder 93)
    - Standard practice instructions, undated (Box 11, Folder 94)
    - U. S. Board of Tax Appeals: petitions, 1936-1940, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 95-98)
  - Alfred P. Sloan Foundation
    - Memos: accounting methods, undated (Box 12, Folder 99)
    - Monthly report form
      - Jaxon Corporation, undated (Box 12, Folder 100)
      - New Castle Corporation, undated (Box 12, Folder 101)
      - Rene Corporation, undated (Box 12, Folder 102)
      - Sloan, Alfred P., Jr.,Esq.: personal, undated (Box 12, Folder 103)
      - Snug Harbor Development Corporation, undated (Box 12, Folder 104)
    - Standard practice instructions
      - Accounting, undated (Box 13, Folder 105)
      - Corporations, undated (Box 13, Folder 106)
      - Files, undated (Box 13, Folder 107)
      - Introduction, undated (Box 13, Folder 108)
      - Investments, undated (Box 13, Folder 109)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 13, Folder 110)
      - Rene Corporation: special, undated (Box 13, Folder 111)
      - Secretarial, undated (Box 13, Folder 112)
      - Sloan, Alfred, P., Jr., Esq.: special, undated (Box 13, Folder 113)
      - Staff members, undated (Box 13, Folder 114)
  - Consultant
    - Miscellaneous, 1914; 1955-1957 (Box 14, Folder 115)
    - Photographs and miscellaneous: Texas Company, 1944, undated (Box 14, Folder 116)
    - Reports
      - National Industrial Conference Board. "Costs and their Relation to the American Enterprise Organization", 1939 (Box 14, Folder 117)
      - Proceedings of the Conferences on Bond Portfolios. "How to Sell Undesired Holdings", 1939 (Box 14, Folder 118)
      - Tenth National Bank, New York. "Mainsprings of the War", 1940 (Box 14, Folder 119)
      - "A Report on an Inter-American Institute", 1941 (Box 14, Folder 120)
      - Texas Company. "A Report on Conditions in Syria, Lebanon, Palestine...and Arabia:, 1944, undated (Box 14, Folder 121)
      - Koppers Company, Inc. "Organization Chart", 1955 (Box 14, Folder 122)
      - Packaging Industries, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 123)
  - American Hemisphere Division, Board of Economic Welfare
    - "Report of the National Research Council on Latin-American Industrial Development...", 1941 (Box 14, Folder 124)
  - Grant and Atkins, Inc.
    - Report: "An Analysis of an Actual but Anonymous Bank and a Report on Policies and Programs...", 1939 (Box 14, Folder 125)
  - Balfour, Guthrie, and Co., Ltd.
    - Clippings, 1941-1944, undated (Box 15, Folder 126-127)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1940-1942, undated (Box 15, Folder 128)
      - Family, 1940-1941, undated (Box 15, Folder 129-131)
    - Lecture tour, 1942 (Box 15, Folder 132)
    - Lectures, 1975, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 133)
    - Maps and guides, 1941 (Box 15, Folder 134)
    - Photographs and postcards, 1940-1941 (Box 15, Folder 135-136)
    - Portugal: printed material, [ca 1937-1942; 1974] (Box 15, Folder 137-139)
    - Reports
      - "Capture of the French S. S. Banfora", 1941 (Box 16, Folder 140)
      - "DeGaulle and the Bombardment of Dakar", 1941 (Box 16, Folder 141)
      - "Military Situation at Dakar, Senegal, A. O. F.", 1941 (Box 16, Folder 142)
      - "Naval Situation at Dakar, Senegal, A. O. F.", 1941 (Box 16, Folder 143)
    - Reports and articles, 1941 (Box 16, Folder 144)
    - Scrapbook pages and miscellanea, [ca1941-1942] (Box 16, Folder 145-146)
    - Travel documents, 1941 (Box 16, Folder 147)
  - Iran-Millspaugh Mission
    - Appointment books, 1943-1944 (Box 17, Folder 148)
    - Clippings, 1942-1944 (Box 17, Folder 149)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1942-1944, undated (Box 17, Folder 150-152)
      - Family, 1942-1944 (Box 17, Folder 153-165)
      - Select
        - Miller, William McE., 1941 (Box 18, Folder 166)
        - Millspaugh, Arthur C.
          - General correspondence, 1943 (Box 18, Folder 167)
          - Memoranda, 1943 (Box 18, Folder 168)
          - Monthly reports, 1943 (Box 18, Folder 169-170)
          - Price stabilization orders, 1943 (Box 18, Folder 171)
    - Proposed Plan for Government Factories, 1943 (Box 18, Folder 172)
    - Regulation for Enforcing the Employees' Aid Law, 1943 (Box 18, Folder 173)
    - Rent stabilization regulations, 1943 (Box 18, Folder 174)
    - Reports
      - "Cahier des Charges Pur L'Extension de la Centrale Electrique de Tehran", 1945 (Box 18, Folder 175)
    - Scrapbook pages, undated (Box 18, Folder 176)
  - American Mission for Aid to Greece
    - Bulletins, 1947-1949, undated (Box 19, Folder 177)
    - Clippings, 1947; 1949 (Box 19, Folder 178)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1947-1950 (Box 19, Folder 179-186)
      - Family, 1947 (Box 19, Folder 187-191)
    - Miscellaneous, 1947, undated (Box 20, Folder 192)
    - Printed material, 1928; 1944; 1947; undated (Box 20, Folder 193-194)
    - Reports
      - "Design of a Program for the Economic Rehabilitation and Development of Greece", 1946 (Box 20, Folder 195-196)
      - "Introductory Report on the Budget for the Financial Year 1946-1947" (Box 20, Folder 197)
      - Information pamphlet and related material, 1947 (Box 20, Folder 198)
      - Various notes on the American Mission for Aid to Greece, 1947 (Box 20, Folder 199)
      - "Plans for a stable means of monetary measurement", 1948 (Box 20, Folder 200)
      - "Notes on the Activities of Paul M. Atkins as Banking and Foreign Exchange Specialist...", 1948 (Box 20, Folder 201)
      - "A Factual Summary Concerning the American Mission for Aid to Greece", 1948 (Box 20, Folder 202)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 20, Folder 203)
    - Resume, undated (Box 20, Folder 204)
  - Japan-Banking adviser
    - Banking: laws and regulations, 1948; undated (Box 21, Folder 205)
    - Banking: Miscellaneous Banks, 1948 (Box 21, Folder 206)
    - Banks
      - Bank of Kobe, 1948 (Box 21, Folder 207)
      - Sumitomo Bank, [ca 1948] (Box 21, Folder 208)
      - Tokai Bank, 1948 (Box 21, Folder 209)
    - Clippings, 1948-1949, undated (Box 21, Folder 210)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1948-1950 (Box 21, Folder 211)
      - Family, 1948 (Box 21, Folder 212-213)
    - Reports
      - "Report on Banking statistics in Japan", 1948 (Box 21, Folder 214)
      - Miscellaneous, 1948, undated (Box 21, Folder 215)
      - "Report on Banking Statistics in Japan", 1948 (Box 21, Folder 216)
    - Scrapbook pages and miscellanea, [ca 1948] (Box 21, Folder 217-218)
  - National Management Council
    - Amos Tuck School of Business Administration: E. C. A. notebook, [ca 1950-1951] (Box 22, Folder 219)
    - Correspondence: family, 1950 (Box 23, Folder 220)
    - Memoranda, 1950-1951 (Box 23, Folder 221-223)
    - Miscellaneous, 1948; 1951; undated (Box 23, Folder 224)
    - Reports
      - "Report on the Recruiting of Technical Personnel for the Aramco Project", 1949 (Box 23, Folder 225)
      - "Criteria for the Selection of Members...", 1951 (Box 23, Folder 226)
      - "Memoranda for N. M. C. Trainees", 1951 (Box 23, Folder 227-231)
      - Miscellaneous, 1951; undated (Box 23, Folder 232)
    - Training Seminars for Foreign Groups
      - British and French, 1951 (Box 23, Folder 233)
      - German, Italian, Swedish, 1951 (Box 23, Folder 234)
  - Rutgers University
    - General